Finding Aid for Danske Udvandrerarkiv (Aalborg universitetscenter) papers, 1873-1923
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Danske Udvandrerarkiv (Aalborg universitetscenter) papers 1873-1923
Aalborg universitetscenter. Danske Udvandrerarkiv.
4 microfilm reels
89180 Bd Microcopy
Danes Worldwide Archives located in Aalborg, Denmark. Collection of materials, largely in Danish, concerning the immigration of Danes to the United States as reflected in letters home, journals, and family histories; also include letters of Danish pastors concerning the work of the church in Ashland, Gowen, and Manistee, Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was made available for microfilming by Aalborg universitetscenter (donor no. 5735 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Danske Udvandrerarkiv (Danes Worldwide Archives ) is located at Aalborg universitetscenter, Aalborg, Denmark.
This microfilm is a selection of letters written from individuals who had immigrated from Denmark to the United States. The letters selected were from individuals who had settled in Michigan communities, notably Ashland, Gowen, and Manistee. Other materials in the collection include journals and family histories.
Subjects:
Ashland (Mich.); Clergy--Michigan.; Danish Americans--Michigan.; Michigan--Emigration and immigration.; Gowen (Mich.); Manistee (Mich.); United States--Emigration and immigration.; Denmark--Emigration and immigration; Immigrants--Michigan.
- Collected materials
  - Peder Kjølhede (pastor at Ashland)
    - Letters, 1879-1885 (Reel 1)
      (arranged by year and then alphabetically by sender)
    - Letters, 1880-1908, from friends, family, and other pastors (Reel 3)
      (arranged alphabetically by sender)
    - Letters, 1887-1892, mainly from the United States and written by Danish Lutheran pastors and parishioners (Reel 4)
      (The letters are postmarked Greenville, Manistee, Racine, Des Moines, Chicago, and other locations.)
  - Julius Petersen
    - Letters, 1887-1921, to his brother Rasmus (both of Chicago) (Reel 1)
      (The letters contain explanatory notes by their brother Karl who remained in Denmark and preserved their letters.)
    - Letters, 1887-1921, of Julius and Rasmus Petersen to brother Karl in Denmark (Reel 2)
      (The letters are written from Chicago, California, Colorado, and discuss the work of Julius as a gold miner and Rasmus as an employee of various Danish-American newspapers. Included is Karl Petersen's family history, his description of letters from America, and his description of Rasmus' visit home in 1896.)
  - P.S. Vig (author of Danish in Amerika)
    - Notes for manuscript and letters on Danes in the war (Reel 2)
  - Alfred E. Grann and wife (Birmingham, Michigan engineer)
    - Clippings, 1951-1952, and family history (Reel 2)
  - Ole Amble (of Gowen, Michigan)
    - Interview (typed in English) with Amble about the Danish Lutheran Church in Gowen (Montcalm County) (Reel 2)
  - Hans Jørgen Pedersen (pastor in Minnesota and Ashland)
    - Biography and letters of the Ashland Church. (Reel 2)
      (Jørgen came to Gowen in 1875.)
  - Mrs. Christiane Hansen (of Manistee, Michigan).
    - Family history; include information concerning Pastor Jorgen Hansen who came to Danish Church in Manistee in 1884 (Reel 2)
  - Simon Kjems (pastor and teacher at Ashland folk high school)
    - Article about his trip in 1891 (Reel 2)
  - A. S. Nielsen (Danish Evangelical Lutheran pastor; called to Chicago, August 4, 1878)
    - Letters from his church members and other pastors in American Danish church, ca. 1870s and 1880s (Reel 3)
      (Include four letters from Rev. H. J. Pedersen of Gowen ( April 23, 1879, March 13 and 24, 1880, October 27, 1883)
  - N. C. Christensen (and others)
    - Letters to family and friends in Denmark from Kansas and Chicago, 1870s and 1880s (Reel 3)
  - Ole Mikkelsen
    - Biography of Arnold Andersen (Reel 3)
  - Peter Jensen (of Racine, Wisconsin)
    - Letters, 1905-1923 to his parents in Denmark concerning his job, schooling, and life in America (Reel 3)
  - J. U. Heiberg (pastor who served in Chicago, 1873-1879, then returned to Denmark where he was an influential member of the Church board concerned with the church in America)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, diary, biographical sketch, and log of his visit of Danish churches in the United States in 1892 (Reel 4)
      (include stops at Muskegon, Gowen, Ashland Folk High School, and at Manistee.)
Related Material
The library has a separate collection of the sermons of Peder Kjølhede.